Guide to the Art Poster File ca. 1890-1910 (bulk 1895-1896) PR 55-1
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
Art Poster File
[1890]-1910, (bulk 1895-1896)
PR 55-1
@ 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.42 Linear feet (612 posters)
The Art Posters include advertisements for books, magazines, and newspapers
Provenance
The posters come from a variety of donors.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to thirty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. See guidelines in Print Room for details.
Historical Note
These posters were produced during a brief American art poster craze, launched in the 1890s when New York publishers hired illustrators Aubrey Beardsley, Elisha Brown Bird, William H. Bradley, George Reiter Brill, William L. Carqueville, George Wharton Edwards, Charles Dana Gibson, Archie Gunn, Ernest Haskell, Edward Penfield, Nelly Umbstaetter, Henry Sumner Watson, Charles Hubbard Wright, and others to create striking graphic advertising posters to sell their monthly magazines. The bold, clever images, inspired by French art styles and the Arts and Crafts movement, became so collectible that publishers switched to monthly pictorial covers.
Scope and Content Note
The Art Posters consist of approximately 612 prints including advertisements for books, magazines, and newspapers. Art Posters make up series I of the Poster File (PR 055). The series is divided into three subseries: Book Posters, Newspaper Posters, and Magazine and Journal Posters.
Arrangement
Posters are filed by periodical and by date.
Related Material at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections
Art posters from this same time period can also be found in the Bella C. Landauer Collection of Advertising and Business Ephemera (PR 031). Other posters can be found in the Poster File (PR 055).
Atlantic Monthly Press, publisher; Bachelor of Arts, publisher; Baker & Godwin, printer; Beardsley, Aubrey, 1872-1898, artist.; Bearings, publisher; Bird, Elisha Brown, 1867-1943, artist; Black cat; Bradley, Will, 1868-1962, artist.; Brill, George Reiter, artist; Carqueville, William L., 1871-1946, artist; Century Company, publisher; Century magazine; Chambers, Robert W. (Robert William), 1865-1933, artist; Charles Scribner's Sons, publisher; Cosmopolitan, publisher; Cox, Charles A., artist; Dixon, Maynard, 1875-1946, artist; Dow, Arthur W. (Arthur Wesley), 1857-1922, artist; Edwards, George Wharton, 1859-1950, artist; Flagg, James Montgomery, 1877-1960, artist; Gibson, Charles Dana, 1867-1944, artist; Godey's magazine; Gould, Joseph J., artist; Gunn, Archie, b. 1863, artist; Harper & Brothers, publisher; Harper's magazine; Haskell, Ernest, 1876-1925, artist; Hazenplug, Frank, 1874-1931, artist; Henslow, W. W. (William Wallace), 1856-1915, artist; Illustrated American; J.B. Lippincott Company, publisher; Kendall, William Sergeant, 1869-1938, artist; Leyendecker, J. C., 1874-1951, artist; Lippincott's magazine; McClure's magazine; McManus, Blanche, b. 1869, artist; Murphy, Nelly Littlehale, artist; New York herald tribune; New York Sunday journal; New York times; New York world (New York, N.Y.: 1861); Outing (1885); Parrish, Maxfield, 1870-1966, artist; Penfield, Edward, 1866-1925, artist; Peterson magazine; Philadelphia press (Philadelphia, Pa.: 1880); Prang's chromo; Recreation; Reed, Ethel, artist; Rhead, Louis, 1857-1926, artist; Scotson-Clark, G. F. (George Frederick), 1872-1927, artist; Scribner's magazine; St. Nicholas (New York, N.Y.); The Bookman, publisher; The Chap-book; The Echo, publisher; The Sun; To Date; Vanity fair (New York, N.Y.); Watson, Henry Sumner, 1868-1933, artist; Wright, Charles Hubbard, artist; Young ladies' journal (American ed.); Advertising -- Books -- Posters; Advertising -- Periodicals -- Posters; Book & magazine posters -- 19th century; Lithographs; Prints
- Subseries I: Book Posters
  Scope and Contents note
  Subseries I. contains 100 posters that date from 1890 to 1907. These posters advertise individual or several books from the same publisher. Publishing companies include Charles Scribner's Sons, Century Co., D. Appleton and Co., Dodd, Mead and Co., Harper and Bros., J.B. Lippincott Co., all of New York, and Lee and Shephard of Boston.
  Book Posters are filed alphabetically by book title. All the posters are housed in flat files, only a folder number is given.
  - Book Posters A-B, 1893-1896, undated (Folder 1)
    General note
    See also: Folder 10
  - Book Posters C-D, 1895-1899, undated (Folder 2)
  - Book Posters E-H, 1895-1907 (Folder 3)
  - Book Posters I-J, 1893-1896 (Folder 4)
  - Book Posters K-L, 1890-1897, undated (Folder 5)
  - Book Posters M-O, 1894-1903 (Folder 6)
  - Book Posters P-R, 1893-1896, undated (Folder 7)
  - Book Posters S-T, 1895-1896, undated (Folder 8)
  - Book Posters U-Z, 1895-1898 (Folder 9)
  - Oversize Book Posters, 1896 (Folder 10)
- Subseries II: Newspaper Posters
  Subseries II. Newspaper Posters contains 134 posters from 1895 and 1896. Posters primarily advertise New York daily and Sunday papers. A few posters from other East Coast cities are also included.
  Newspaper Posters are organized alphabetically by periodical, and then filed by date. All the posters are housed in flat files, only a folder number is given.
  - Miscellaneous, 1895-1896, undated (Folder 11)
  - New York [Times Sunday] Journal, 1891-1896 Mar. (Folder 12)
  - New York [Times Sunday] Journal, 1896 Apr.-Dec. (Folder 13)
  - New York [Times Sunday] Journal, undated (Folder 14)
  - New York Sunday Press, 1895 Apr.-1896 Jan. (Folder 15)
  - New York Sunday World, 1895 (Folder 16)
    See also: Folder 19
  - New York Sunday World, 1896 Jan. - May. (Folder 17)
  - New York Sunday World, 1896 Jun. - Dec. (Folder 18)
  - New York Sunday World Oversize, 1895 Apr. - Jun. (Folder 19)
  - New York Tribune, 1896, undated (Folder 20)
  - Philadelphia Press, 1895-1896 (Folder 21)
- Subseries III: Magazine and Journal Posters
  Subseries III. Magazine and Journal Posters contains 378 posters that date from 1890 to 1910.
  Posters are filed alphabetically by journal and then chronologically. Most of these posters are housed in flat files, and only a folder number is given. Several of the Harper's posters drawn by Harry Penfield are stored in a box.
  - A-C General, 1890-1898, undated (Folder 22)
  - The Bachelor of Arts, 1895-1896 (Folder 23)
  - Bearings, 1895-1896, undated (Folder 24)
  - The Black Cat, 1895-1896 (Folder 25)
  - The Bookman, 1895-1902, undated (Folder 26)
    See also: Folder 53
  - The Century, 1891-1894 (Folder 27)
  - The Century, 1895 (Folder 28)
  - The Century, 1896 (Folder 29)
  - The Century, 1897-1901 (Folder 30)
  - The Chap-Book, 1894-1896 (Folder 31)
  - The Cosmopolitan, 1895 (Folder 32)
  - D-H General, 1895-1910, undated (Folder 33)
  - Harper's, 1894-1895 (Folder 34)
    See also: Penfield Box
  - Harper's, 1896 (Folder 35)
  - Harper's, 1897-1910 (Folder 36)
    See also: Folder 52, Penfield Box
  - I - L General, 1895-1898, undated (Folder 37)
  - Lippincott's, 1894 (Folder 38)
  - Lippincott's, 1895 (Folder 39)
  - Lippincott's, 1896 (Folder 40)
  - M-O General, 1895-1896, undated (Folder 41)
  - McClure's, 1895-1898, undated (Folder 42)
  - Outing, 1894-1895 (Folder 43)
  - Outing, 1896, undated (Folder 44)
  - P-R General, 1894-1898, undated (Folder 45)
  - Recreation, 1896 (Folder 46)
  - S-U General, 1894-1898, undated (Folder 47)
  - St. Nicholas, 1895-1896, undated (Folder 48)
    See also: Folder 52
  - Scribner's, 1894-1896 (Folder 49)
  - Scribner's, 1896-[1900] (Folder 50)
  - V-Z General, 1895-1899, undated (Folder 51)
  - Oversize posters for Scribner's, Harper's, and St. Nicholas, 1895-1897 (Folder 52)
  - Oversize posters, 1895-1901 (Folder 53)